\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-345/780 Laboratory I

Introduction

The goal of this laboratory session is to familiarize you with the laboratory, using your account, and managing projects. It uses the pipelined multiplier handed out in class on September 13 as the project to work with.

Procedure

Log into your account and set up a workspace and a project.

Log into any one of the computers in A-227 using your account name for this course, which consists of the first letter of your first name, your last name, and the digits “345” or “780”all as a single lower-case string. That is, if you are an undergraduate and your name is "Always A. Good Student", your account name is astudent345. Use the password given to you in class, and remember that you will be required to change it to something secure the first time you log in.

The names of the computers are:

A-205 | A-227
birch | apple
cherry | fir
chestnut | juniper
elm | mimosa
ginkgo | peach
hemlock | pine
hickory | plum
  | spruce
  | sycamore
  | walnut

Room 205 is an “open lab,” which means you can use the computers there any time you want. The secretaries in the CS Department Office (A-202) will open the lab for you if it is closed. Room 227 is a closed lab, available only during class times. However, all of the computers are accessible from the Internet. If you have access to a computer running Windows XP with a broadband connection, you can use Remote Desktop to log in. From the Start button, go to Programs, to Accessories, to Communications, and you will find it. When it asks you what computer you want to connect to, pick one of the names above and add the domain name “.cs.qc.edu” to the computer name. For example, you would log into ginkgo by entering ginkgo.cs.qc.edu.

When you use Remote Desktop, select one of the computers in A-227 so that students who are on campus will be able to use the computers in A-205. The exception, of course, is when our class uses room A-227 between 5:00 and 6:15 pm on Tuesdays and Thursdays.

Use Windows Explorer to verify that your “My Documents” directory contains a directory named “My Projects.”

Start the DK GUI and create a new workspace. Use your My Projects directory as the path to the workspace. Use cs345 or cs780 as the workspace name. This should immediately create an empty directory named cs345 in your My Projects directory.

Add a project named Multiplier to your workspace. Select "core" as the type of project. Exit DK.

Verify that you have created a file named cs345.hw in your My Projects\cs345 directory. [From here on, substitute “780” as necessary in these instructions.] Make sure there is a subdirectory named Multiplier, and that there is a Multiplier.hp file in the project directory.

Log off the computer you used and log into another one.

On the second computer, verify that your workspace and project directories and their files appear on the second computer, indicating that your “profile” (settings) were successfully copied to the domain server (maple) when you logged off the first computer and that they were then copied to the second computer when you logged into it. If you have any problems with this step, contact Dr. Vickery for help before proceeding with the remainder of the assignment.

Add the multiplier.hcc file to the project, edit the multiplier code, and simulate it.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-345/780 Laboratory II

Introduction

This laboratory session introduces two major items: (1) using the Platform Abstraction Layer (PAL) libraries to accomplish I/O tasks, and (2) using the EDIF design flow to generate “bit” files and downloading them to an RC200E kit for testing.

The applications itself is simple: use two seven segment displays to show the hexadecimal representation of the ASCII codes for characters typed on a keyboard.

Procedure

Configure a new project for both Debug and EDIF design flows.

Start DK, and re-open the workspace you created in Laboratory I. Create a new project in that workspace named Keybd2SevenSeg. How you spell the project name doesn’t matter much, but you can make things easier if you don’t put any spaces in the project name. In the New Project dialog box, select “Xilinx Virtex-II Chip,” which is the type of FPGA on the RC-200 kits.

This step is optional, but it might make it easier to manage the project if you do it. From the Build menu, select Configurations, and delete all the configurations for this project except Debug and EDIF. (You will be deleting Release, VHDL, Verilog, SystemC, and Generic.)

At this point it’s time to do some one-time setting up of DK itself. Under the Tools menu select Options, and make the following changes: go to the Tabs panel and click the indent spaces radio button, set the tab size to 2, and make sure auto-indent is checked. On the Format panel, select the output Category and change the font to Monaco, Courier, or Fixedsys. (Some of the output messages are tables that don’t line up right if you use a proportional font.)

Set the Debug Configuration options.

Be sure your new project is the active project. Go to Project -> Settings, select the Debug choice from the drop-down list, go to the Preprocessor tab, and add USE_SIM to the comma separated list of preprocessor defintions. Go to the Linker tab and add the following libraries as a comma separated list in the Object/library modules box: stdlib.hcl, pal_sim.hcl, sim.hcl, and pal_keyboard.hcl

In the “Additional C/C++ Modules” box of the Linker tab, enter the following pathname: C:\Program Files\Celoxica\PDK\Software\Lib\PalSim.lib

Other projects for this course will use the same settings for simulation except that pal_keyboard.hcl will only be used for keyboard projects, and other libraries may occasionally be added to the first list.

Type in the program and simulate it.

Be sure it works! Type in different scan codes and be sure they display the correct ASCII values. There is a chart with the scan codes in ms_scancodes.pdf.

Set up the EDIF design flow and test the hardware.

Select the EDIF build configuration, and enter the following values: add USE_RC200E to the list of preprocessor defintions; on the Chip panel, enter XC2V1000FG456-4 as the Part; on the linker tab, use stdlib.hcl, pal_rc200e.hcl, rc200e.hcl, and pal_keyboard.hcl as the libraries list. Finally, on the Build commands panel, view Commands and enter the following two lines: “cd EDIF” (no quotes) and “edifmake_rc200 Keybd2SevenSeg” again with no quotes, but if your project name has any spaces in it you have to put quotes around its name. Switch the view to Outputs, and enter the single line: EDIF.

Build the project, making sure there are no errors or warnings, and use the FTU2 program to download and test your bit file.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-345/780 Laboratory IV

Introduction

This is a continuation of Laboratory III in which you will use some addtional features of Handel-C to add a visual effect to your seven segment display of ASCII codes. The visual effect is to have each character code fade away after it is first displayed. The Handel-C features you are to use are channels, macro procs, and libraries.

Procedure

Configure a new library project.

Start DK, and re-open the workspace you created in Laboratory I. Create a new project in that workspace named delayProcs. Select Library as the project type.

Delete all the configurations for this project except Generic. You do not have to set any configuration options for this project.

Write a millisecond delay macro proc.

You can control time intervals in Handel-C if you know the speed of the clock you are working with, how long an interval you want, and the fact that each assignment statement takes exactly one clock cycle.

Write a macro proc named msecDelay that takes two parameters: a number of milliseconds and the speed of the clock. The macro is to take exactly the specified number of milliseconds to execute. There are several ways to accomplish this, but here is the “standard” approach: The number of clock pulses per millisecond is the number of clock pulses per second (the clock rate passed as the second paramter) divided by 1,000. Multiply pulses per milliseconds by the desired number of milliseconds (the first parameter), and you have the number of pulses to use up. This value should be determined at compile time, so use a macro expr to compute it. Set up a register with enough bits to hold this value, using the log2ceil() from the standard library to establish its width. Initialize the register with a count of the number of pulses you need, and use a while loop to decrement the register until it reaches zero. Think about how to get exactly the correct number of statements executed by the macro — not that anyone will actually know if you are off by a one or two clock pulses.

When you build this project, you will get a library file named delayProcs.hcl in the Generic subdirectory of the project. Later on you can add other procs to this library, for example to delay for a number of microseconds instead of milliseconds.

To guarantee, as much as possible, that the code that uses your macro proc calls it correctly, you need to supply a function prototype for it that both the definition and the references both use. Add a Handel-C header file named delayProcs.hch to the delayProcs project, and put the following code in it:

// delayProcs.hch #ifndef __DELAY_PROCS__ #define __DELAY_PROCS__ extern macro proc msecDelay(msec, clockRate); #endif

Use a #include directive to include this header file in msecDelay.hcc. It seems strange to declare the procedure external in the file in which it is defined, but that’s the standard way to manage prototypes. Because this header file is not in a standard place, you have to put the file name in quotes rather than angle brackets.

Test your delay procedure

Modify your keybd2video.hcc from the Laboratory III project so that it includes the header file for your library, and add the library to the list of library modules for both the Debug and EDIF build configurations.

Add a third endless loop to this project that reads from a channel, sets the foreground color to its default value, uses msecDelay() to execute for one second, and then sets the foreground color to match the background color. Add a line to the endless loop that reads from the keyboard so that it writes to the channel every time a character is typed. The value written to the channel and read from it is irrelevant for this project; I suggest you declare the channel’s data type as unsigned 1, and simply write either a 0 or a 1 to it, whichever you prefer.

The effect should be that typing a character causes its ASCII code to display for one second and then disappear.

Add the fade effect.

Modify the loop you just added to the project so that instead of simply changing the foreground color in a single step at the end of one second, it changes the foreground color gradually, in at least 64 steps, spanning one or two seconds. To get a smooth transition, you will have to adjust the red, green, and blue components individually. Your algorthm must work independently of the actual foreground and background colors in effect, forcing you deal with the possibility that you will have to work with fractional intensity values, using simple fixed point numbers as described in class.

Submit Laboratories I through IV

If you have not already done so, be sure all the code you have written so far is “clean.” Things to check for are: proper indentation to show the logical structure with no tab charcters in the code, all lines of code narrow enough to display in a normal panel without wrapping (80 columns), and comments to show the logical structure of the code. Set off each macro proc and function defintion with some sort of horizontal line; likewise for each endless loop:

// main() // -------------------------------------------------------- /* * Meaningful comments. */ void main(void) { ... }

When your laboratories are ready for me to look at, send me an email message with “CS-345 First Laboratories” or “CS-780 First Laboratories” as the subject. Be sure to put at least your name inside your message. If you worked with someone else, be sure to list everyone’s name and to tell me which account has the code. (If a graduate student and undergraduate student worked together, the subject line can be either of the ones listed, or a mix.)

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-345/780 Laboratory V

Servomotor Controller

Introduction

In this laboratory, you will explore direct interaction between the FPGA and the “outside world.” Until now, you performed all input and output operations using the macros in the Platform Abstraction Layer (PAL), which sheilded you from the nitty-gritty of actually manipulating the voltage values on the FPGA pins. With this project your PAL-provided innocence expires.

As you know, the Simulation design flow allows you to debug your code both by monitoring its external behavior on the PAL Virtual Console, and by examining its internal state using the DK simulator. But for this project, you are using a device that is not supported by the PAL Virtual Console, namely a small servomotor that is controlled using pulse width modulation (PWM). Not only do you not have the PAL Virtual Console for feedback, but you also have to deal with the fact that the DK simulator does not provide the real-time timing information you need to check whether your pulse width modulation code is actually modulating pulse widths correctly. So this project introduces you to the use of two tools for testing (and debugging) the timing of your design. One is an extension to the DK simulation software, called the Waveform Analyzer. In addition, you will practice using an oscilloscope to check the actual waveforms generated by your design. Finally, you will connect a servomotor to the RC200E and verify that your program actually does control the motor correctly.

Controller Description

The servomotor you will be controlling, the Futaba S3003, is normally used to operate radio controlled model airplanes, cars, or boats. Normally, when it receives pulses of one width, the motor shaft rotates clockwise about a quarter turn and when it receives pulses of a different width, it rotates in the opposite direction. It has an internal circuit that senses its own displacement clockwise or counterclockwise and returns the motor to its “neutral” position when no pulses are applied. This design is great for steering planes, cars, and boats, but cannot be used to make cars or robots move — at least not very far. So a popular modification is to modify the motor mechanically to remove the stop that prevents 360° rotation, and the linkage between the shaft position sensor (a potentiometer) and the shaft. The motors in the lab have been modified this way.

The servomotor has three wires connected to it: a black one that goes to ground, a red one that connects to a positive voltage betwen 4.8 and 6.0 volts, and a white one that receives control pulses. We have rigged connectors so the motors can be connected to the 50-pin “expansion header” on the side of the RC200. Pin 46 of the expansion header provides +5VDC, eight pins supply ground, and 34 of the pins are connected to the I/O pins of the FPGA. When you plug the motor connector into the expansion header, the red wire goes to Pin 46, the black wire goes to Pin 50 (one of the ground connections), and the white wire goes to Pin 38, which is connected to I/O pin “V2” of the FPGA.

To make the motor work, it must receive a 50 Hz pulse train. If the width of the pulses is 1 msec the motor rotates in one direction; if the width of the pulses is 2 msec, the motor rotates in the opposite direction, and if the width of the pulses is 1.5 msec, the motor stops rotating. When your controller is finished, it will generate a continuous 50 Hz pulse stream on FPGA Pin M3. The two pushbuttons on the side of the RC200E will modify the width of the pulses as follows: initially, the pulse width will be 1.5 msec; pressing button 0 will increment or decrement the pulse width by 10 µsec, and pressing button 1 will control whether button 0 adds to or subtracts from the pulse width. By providing such fine control over the pulse widths, you should be able to control not only the direction of rotation, but also the speed.

Procedure

Start a new project.

Create a new project named “Motor_Controller” for this laboratory. Configure it for Simulation and EDIF in the usual way, with the following differences:

Instead of defining PAL_TARGET_CLOCK_RATE with a #define preprocessor directive, do it in the Preprocessor tab of the Project Settings panel. Where you specify USE_xxx, add PAL_TARGET_CLOCK_RATE=50000000 for the EDIF configuration. But for Simulation, specify a 1 MHz clock instead of 50 MHz. The reason for using such a low clock rate for simulation is to help make using the Waveform Analyzer a bit easier as discussed below. By specifying the two different clock rates here, you avoid the need for conditional compilation in your source code later.
On the same Preprocessor tab, put the relative path to the directory containing your delayProcs.hch file in the “Additional Include Directories” box. Now you will be able to include your header file using angle brackets instead of quotes, and won’t have to type in the path to the directory in your code either
Finally, on the Linker tab, put the relative pathname to your library file’s directory in the Additional Library Path box, and remove the path component from the library name.

The previous assignment should have used the second two items above, but it’s not too late to make things right!

Add usecDelay() to your delayProcs library.

You need finer timing control for this project than your msecDelay() provides. Update delayProcs.hch to include the function prototype for a macro proc that delays for a specified number of microseconds (µsec) rather than milliseconds. Add a second Handel-C source file to the library project with your new usecDelay() procedure in it.

Optional:

Use a Handel-C assert() statement to generate the width of the counter register. If the number of ticks is not greater than 0, the assertion should fail, reporting the delay interval and clock speed passed as parameters. Test the assertion by calling the macro with a short interval and slow clock speed.

Use the buttons to change values and seven segment displays to show them.

Create a source file for the laboratory named motor_controller.hcc if you have not done so already. Write code so that pressing button 0 makes the seven segment displays count upward from 00 to 99 in decimal. Think in terms of two Binary Coded Decimal (BCD) digits. Each button press and release must make the counter increment by exactly one; this is an exercise in “debouncing” the button, as described in class. You may cause the count to increment on either the press or the release, but not both. Now make it so that pressing button 1 makes the displays count downwards instead of upwards. Turn on the right decimal point when counting up and turn it off when counting down. Automatically switch directions if the user tries to count up beyond 99 or down below 00.

Even if the code works properly on the RC200E, also make sure it simulates correctly. You will be using the simulator explcitly below, so this part has to work correctly both ways from the beginning.

Do not use division! Avoid the temptation to use a single register to hold the value of the counter and to use divide and mod to break it into decimal digits. Or don’t believe me, try it, and see how much of the FPGA your design uses and how long it takes to build!

Simulate code that outputs to a pin.

Define a 1-bit unsigned integer named controlPin, and another variable named pulseWidth that can hold a value that ranges from 100 to 200. The former will output the pulses to the motor, and the latter will tell how wide each pulse is, in hundredths of a millisecond. That is, a pulseWidth value of 100 will be 1 msec, 150 will be 1.5 msec, and 200 will be 2 msec. Add logic to your code so that pulseWidth and the seven segment displays are synchronized. when the seven segment displays show 00, pulseWidth should be 100, 50 on the display corresponds to a pulseWidth of 150, and 99 on the display corresponds to a pulseWidth of 199.

Write two parallel endless loops, and connect them by a 0-bit wide channel. The first loop is to write to the channel at a 50 Hz rate. The second loop, reads from the channel, sets controlPin to 1, delays the number of microseconds given by the current value of pulseWidth, sets controlPin to zero, and waits at the channel again.

Now you need to add code that connects controlPin to the simulator. Look at the Waveform Anlyzer manual in the Celoxica/DK/Documentation directory. The Waveform Analyzier can both show the timing ouf your program’s outputs (what we want) and generate waveforms for input to your program (not of interest to us for this project). So, you are interested in only Chapter 1 of the manual for this assignment, and need to read just the first ten pages before continuing.

Using the Waveform Analyzer manual as a guide, set up your code so you can monitor the value of controlPin. You will have to synchronize the DK simulator’clock with the Waveform Analyzer’s clock, and you will have to connect the value of controlPin to the Waveform Analyzer’s “terminal” interface.

Managing the clock is tricky. If you just use pal_master.hch to generate the value of PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE from PAL_TARGET_CLOCK_RATE, you will get multiple clocks defined for your code: one set clock in pal_master.hch, and a second one that you will need to code following the guidelines of the Waveform Analyzer manual. The trick is to use conditional compilation and to include pal_master after you define PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE explicitly yourself:

#ifdef USE_SIM set clock = external "P1" with { extlib = "DKSync.dll", extinst = "1000", // Period of 1MHz simulated clock in nsec extfunc = "DKSyncGetSet" }; #define PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE PAL_TARGET_CLOCK_RATE interface bus_out() motor( unsigned 1 out = controlPin ) with { extlib = "DKConnect.dll", extinst = "t(1)", extfunc = "DKConnectGetSet" }; #endif #include <pal_master.hch> #ifndef PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE #error "No clock rate specified!" #else macro expr clockRate = PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE; #endif

I apologize for giving you so much code!
Be sure to study it rather than just cutting and pasting blindly.

When you set up your Waveform Analyzer trace window, be sure to specify the correct clock period (in nsec), and set the “Default No. Points” so that one sweep across the window will correspond to exactly one period of the 50 Hz pulse train. The idea is that you want each pulse to display in the same place in the window on each sweep.

When you have this step working correctly, you should be able to observe the PAL Virtual Console and the Waveform Analyzer window at the same time. Clicking on Button 0 on the virtual console should change the value displayed on the seven segment displays, and you should be able to see the effect on the waveform being traced out in the Waveform Analyzer window. Use Waveform Analyzer cursors to verify that the pulses are of the correct width.

Familiarize yourself with the oscilloscopes used in the lab.

Look through the Tektronix “XYZ’s of Oscilloscopes” primer provided to you. You will be working with a Digital Storage Oscilloscope (DSO) to look at waveforms output by the FPGA to the expansion header pins on the side of the RC200E. Look at pages 13-14 for a description of DSOs, pages 18-32 for a description of the various controls on an oscilloscope, and pages 46-47 on probe compensation.

Set up an oscilloscope and compensate the probe.

Configure for EDIF with controlPin connected to an expansion header pin, and monitor the pin using the oscilloscope.

Use conditional compilation to compile the following interface definition if USE_RC200E is defined:

interface bus_out() motor( unsigned 1 out = controlPin ) with { data = { "V2" } };

V2 is the name of the pin on the FPGA that is connected to pin number 38 on the expansion header. (The manual that documents this is in …\Celoxica\PDK\Documentation\PSL\RC20x\Manuals.)

Carefully connect the tip of the oscilloscope probe to pin 38 of the expansion header. It’s the sixth pin from the left on the bottom row; the second one past the empty spot with 42 printed on the circuit board. You will probably get a perfectly good signal with the ground clip disconnected. Download your program to the FPGA and perform the following exercises with the oscilloscope:

First press the “Auto Set” button to have the oscilloscope detect your signal automatically. If necessary, use the trigger menu to select positive edge triggering from channel 1 and use the channel 1 menu to select DC coupling. Bandwidth limiting should be off, volts per division can be either coarse or fine, the probe should auto-detect 10X attenuation; if not, set it to 10X and be sure the switch on the side of the probe is set to 10X too.

Verify that your pulse train is operating at 50 Hz.
Verify that the initial pulse width is exactly 1.5 msec. Use the “Measure” and “Cursor” buttons to measure the pulse width.
Verify that the pulse width changes by 10 µsec each time you press Button 0.

Connect a servomotor to the RC200E and verify that your controller actually works.

If you are sure the pulse parameters are correct on the oscilloscope but the motor “creeps” in one direction or the other when you first start your program, there is a screwdriver adjustment I can make that will stop it.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CS-345/780 Laboratory VI

Touchscreen Chord Generator

Introduction

For this project, you are to build a machine that plays musical chords in response to user presses on the LCD touchscreen. You will need to become familiar with the touchscreen and sound systems of the RC200E, and will need to work with table lookup techniques for generating the audio waveforms.

Project Description

The project is divided into three stages, each of which is to be implemented as a separate DK project in your course workspace.

The first project is to familiarize you with the operation of the touchscreen. In it, you will write a program that displays the coordinates of the points the user touches on the screen and develop a strategy for getting “clean” input data. For this project, you will use the PalConsole API documented in the Pal Cores manual. The PalConsole API provides a somewhat primitive way of writing text strings on the LCD.

The second stage is to introduce you to the audio output functions provided by PalAudioOut, which require you to provide sound intensity values at a defined sampling rate. You might want to work with my Audio Sampling Laboratory before starting this part of the assignment. You will need to build a sine lookup table to work with for this part of the project, which is most easily done by writing a standalone program that generates the source code for a Handel-C array of intensity values.

In the third stage, you will create a Handel-C application that combines the functionality of the first two stages: when the user presses various points on the screen, the device will generate sounds that are various mixtures of three basic frequencies to produce various chords.

Procedure

Create a touchscreen input project.

Create a new project named Touch2Console in your course workspace. Output to the console a line of text that tells the coordinates where the user is touching whenever the user is touching the touchscreen. Read from the touchscreen on every clock cycle, output the value of the touch variable to an expansion header pin, and use an oscilloscope to observe the value of this variable in real time to determine the rate at which touches repeat when the screen is pressed continuously. Observe any patterns you can about what coordinates are reported when touches begin and end, and devise a way to manage the touch data cleanly.

Create an audio output project.

The Nyquist sampling theorem says you need to sample a waveform at twice the rate of the maximum frequency component to in order to reproduce the waveform accurately. Write a program that generates a 10KHz sine wave with the sampling rate determined by a compile time constant. Try sampling rates of 2, 5, 10, and 20 KHz and see if you can hear the difference.

Generate_PAL_Samples.java

Build the chord generator

Lay out the touchscreen so there are three zones where touches will generate tones with frequencies in a ratio of 4:5:6. You can use any base frequency you want: 440Hz is a common starting point. Touching three other places generates pairs of tones from the above set, and touching another zone generates the full chord of all three tones mixed together.

Vickery Home - This term - Course Home
XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .